<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bits of Experience (Posts about macroeconomics)</title><link>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/categories/macroeconomics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:marco.hassan30@gmail.com"&gt;Marco Hassan&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 18:25:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Macro Variables</title><link>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/macro-variables/</link><dc:creator>Marco Hassan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
So here some notes about the macro side of the coin.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I started reading the &lt;a href="https://www.zurich.com/en/economics-and-markets/publications"&gt;weekly publications&lt;/a&gt; of the macro-group of
Zurich.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I must say that it is interesting. I always loved macro.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I always recall the book of Blanchard. I think that this was the most
intersting theories I read throughout my academic life. Stat is
nice.. but way too much low level that higher world modeling dimension
is missing.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I mean think Black-Scholes. That is also fun if I think about it now
again. A simple mathematical formula - confusing tons of
practitioners - through that stat low level stuff moving trillions of
dollars which is then ultimately resulting from very questionable
first-order assumptions.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes I am fascinated about how this world sticks together and is
not simply falling apart. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Anyways, back to Macroeconomics, at some point I thought that my life
was gonna be around it. &lt;i&gt;Kaynes vs. Hayek&lt;/i&gt; in an endless pointless
fight.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I think that there is an inherent beauty in observing that
macro-picture making guesses about how the dots are connected.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Speculating on the reaction of CB etc. lovely. At the end they all
follow the common principles. Until the "business" does not require a
big shift.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In any case here the list - which I guess will keep expanding in the
coming years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It is important to understand all of these different components as if
you will stay for a long time in the industry and you will manage to
navigate data quickly some interesting patterns might start to emerge.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/macro-variables/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>finance</category><category>macroeconomics</category><guid>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/macro-variables/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 15:16:45 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>