<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Bits of Experience (Posts about Simulation)</title><link>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/categories/simulation.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2022 &lt;a href="mailto:marco.hassan30@gmail.com"&gt;Marco Hassan&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 06:56:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Gibbs Sampler</title><link>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/Gibbs-Sampler/</link><dc:creator>Marco Hassan</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post explores the Gibbs sampler algorithm. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In Bayesian Statistics sometimes it is not possible to integrate
analytically over the posterior distribution. It is hence not possible
to minimize over the loss function spanned by the posterior
distribution of the parameters of interest in order to take the bayes
decision.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A solution in this case is to leverage simulation to obtain an
i.i.d. sample of the posterior distribution of the parameters of
interest. Given an i.i.d. sample of it is then possible to leverage
the properties of the CLT to get an unbiased estimate of the
parameters of interest. This is for instance the backbone of
simulation methods such as Monte Carlo.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A further evolution consists in generating a dependent sample from the
distribution of interest through a reversible Markov Chain. In such a
case it is possible to prove that the series generated from the Markov
Chain will converge to the stationary equilibrium of the Chain -
i.e. the distribution of interest - such that it is possible at a
later stage to apply the CLT to the converged series to obtain
estimates and CI for the parameters of interest.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this sense the Gibbs Sampler is an algorithm generating explicitly
a reversible Markov Chain that gives the opportunity to obtain
estimates for the parameter of interest from a nasty, analytically not
integrable posterior distribution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To illustrate the algorithm the post looks now at the simple case of
sampling from a bivariate distribution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/Gibbs-Sampler/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Simulation</category><guid>https://marcohassan.github.io/bits-of-experience/posts/Gibbs-Sampler/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 13:00:53 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>